University of Connecticut, History Department Records 1999.0039
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, History Department Records
1951-2006
1999.0039
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.25 Linear feet
Materials pertaining to the programs and activities of the department.The collection contains materials from the history department during from the 1950s through the early twenty-first century. It contains the department's administrative records, along with correspondence, news clippings, notes, publications, financial records, and awards.
University of Connecticut. Department of History
History
The history department provides an environment to study the diversity of human experience across time space, and helps students develop skills that enable them to understand the complex ways the past shapes the present and future. Through the department's courses and programs, it seeks not only to train future historians but to produce thoughtful and well-informed citizens. Graduates of the department have successfully pursued careers in business, public service, museum work, public history, law, and various other professions. In addition to offering a major and a minor in history, the department also offers graduate programs, with a Master's and a Ph.D. in Medieval European, Early Modern and Modern Europe, United States and Latin American history.
More information about the department and its faculty, programs and events is available on its website.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials about the programs of the history department during from the 1950s through the early twenty-first century. The collection is divided into two series, and contains administrative records, along with correspondence, news clippings, notes, publications, financial records, and awards. The series are divided between records dating from primarily the 1970s, and records consisting of documents from the 1950s to the present.
The first series contains administrative records concerning the department's activities for the American Bicentennial as well as curriculum revisions. The addition to the collection, donated in 2010, contains a varitey of materials from the department from the 1950s to 2006. Subjects in the collection include the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), Departmental Advisory Committee, Afro-American History Month and Cultural Center, American Antiquarian Society, American Historical Association, Alumni Association Awards, American Association for State and Local History, American Studies Program, University Archives, Asian-American Studies, Homer Babbidge History Dept. Chair Files, UConn Bicentennial Lectures, and University of Connecticut Branch campuses at Hartford, Avery Point, Stamford, Torrington, and Waterbury.
Acquisition Information
Transferred to Archives & Special Collections by the history department faculty in 1999 and 2010.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Academic department.; Administrative Records.; American Revolution Bicentennial, 1776-1976—Connecticut.; College teaching—United States—History.; Correspondence.; Curriculum change—United States—History.; History—Study and teaching.; Reports.; Universities and colleges—United States—Curricula—History.; University of Connecticut—Curricula—History.
- Series I: Records, 1974-1978
  - American Bicentennial, 1975-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Revisions, 1976-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - European Curriculum Revision, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Planning Committee, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Undergraduate Program Needs and Goals, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
- Series II: An Inventory, 1951-2006; 9.1 Linear feet
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Publications, Clippings, Financial Records, Notes, 1969-2006; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects Include: American Association of University Professors (AAUP), Office of Provost Academic Program Planning Evaluation and Goals, Accredation Survey, Departmental Advisory Committee, Afro-American History Month and Cultural Center, American Antiquarian Society, American Historical Association, Alumni Association Awards, American Association for State and Local History, American Studies Program, University Archives, Asian-American Studies, Athletes Intercollegiate, Homer Babbidge History Dept. Chair Files, Bachelor General Studies Degree Program, UConn Bicentennial Lectures, University of Connecticut Branchs of Hartford, Southeastern, Stamford, Torrington, Waterbury, Budget Crisis, Building Names Committee.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Publications, Clippings, Financial Records, Notes, 1973-1998; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_2)
    Subjects Include: Capital Budget Request, Wood Hall Floor Plan, Capital Campaign Meetings, CASE/DANA Awards, CASE Professor of Year, Centenial (UCONN), Centennial Times, The University of Connecticut Chronicle, Center of Black Studies, Center for East Asian Studies, Center for Slavic and European Studies, Center for Study of Human Values, Center for Innovative Education, Options Newsletter, Cheating Records, Department Heads CLAS, Commencement, Committees (History Department), Killeen, Conduct Code Student Employees, Connecticut Historical Commission, Connecticut Humanities Council, Connecticut Center for Independent Historians and Newsletter, Connecticut Medal "They Dare to Speak Out", Convocation of 350th Connecticut Anniversary, Cooperative Education, Core Curriculum, Correspondence: Stave, Curriculum and Courses.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Clippings, Notes, Publications, Financial Records, Awards, 1954-1997; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_3)
    Subjects Include: Committee on Curriculum and Courses, Course Credit by Exam, Curricula and Courses Committee History Department, CLAS, Curriculm and Courses Senate, Curriculum Diversity Handout, Curriculum Revisions, Distinguished Alumni Professor, Diversity and Equity, Employee Benefits, Employee Recognition Program, Emergency Closings, Enrollment Statistics Registrars Office, Enrollment Analysis, CLAS Enrollment and Preregistration Figures, Enrollment Figures, European Studies, Extended and Continuing Education, University of Connecticut Bulletin, Faculty Exchanges, 50th Anniversary of History Department, D.A.R./Anne Wood Elderkin Award, Financial Aid (T.A.S.), Ford Foundation, Edward Victor Gant Scholarship, Hagley Fellowship, Alumini Book and Article Prize, Lougee Fellowship, Nevins Prize, Predoctoral Fellowship, Sturbridge Village Graduate Fellowship, Summer Fellowships, Fullbright Program, V.F.W. Ladies Award.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Publications, Clippings, Fliers, Financial Records, 1951-2000; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_4)
    Subjects Include: General Education Requirements, Graduate Review Committee, Graduate School Guidelines, Graduate School Communications and Correspondence, Graduate Students Association, Grants and Contracts, GRE, Health and Safety Committee, Hiring Information, History Convocation 350th Anniversary, History Courses (211, 297W, 298, W, 401, 402), State History Day, Historical Information History Department, History Survey 1977, Honors Program, Independent Historians Connecticut, Bureau of Institutional Research, Institute-International Interculutural Studies, Italian Studies, Journalism Course, Judaic Studies, Labor Education, Latin American Studies, Learning Disabled Program, Lecturers Policy, Library.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Clippings, Publications, Fliers, Financial Records, 1965-2002; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_5)
    Subjects Include: Library Collection Development in History, Linkage through Language, Litchfield Historical Society, Major Monday, Maritime Studies Program, Brian McMahon Lectures, Medical Insurance Plans and Coverage, History of Medicine, Mellon Fellowship Program, Metanonia Day, Military History, Minority Graduate Students, Mission Statement, Munson Institute, Mystic Seaport, National Archives, NDEA-Title IV, National Coordination Committee for Promotion of History, NEH Grant, New England Historical Association, History Department Newsletter, Newsletter Spring 1984, Northeastern Association of Graduate Schools, Oral History, Organization of American Historians.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Clippings, Financial Records, Notes, Publications, 1969-2002; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_6)
    Subjects Include: Parking Committee, Phi Alpha Theta, Phi Beta Kappa, Placement, Policy Statements, Polish Studies, Political Science, Project 2000, Publications, Publicity-Campus, Public-History Department Publicity, Miscellaneous, Radio and TV, Ratings- Dept/University, Recruiting Students, Research Expertise Directory, Retirement Committee, U of C, R.O.T.C., Salaries-Faculty, Secretarial Postions, Dorthy Culp Scholarships, Senate Meetings (Executive Committee, Faculty Standards Committee, Scholastic Requirments Committee, Small Grants Program, Social Studies Conferences, Strategy Planning Management Committee, Study Abroad, Old Starbridge Village.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Publications, Fliers, Notes, 1970-2002; 1.3 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs, in alphabetical order. (Box 2010-0095_7)
    Subjects Include: Tax Information- Graduate Students, Theft/Break-Ins, Tution, Commission on Unversity Governance, UCEPA Policies, Undergraduate Program, Urban Studies, Threshold, Video Project, Western European Studies